What happens when your bank becomes a
weapon? All over the world, people are
being debanked, cut off from their
money, not because they broke the law,
but because they held the wrong beliefs
or supported the wrong causes. That's
what happened to Pancquake, a privacy
focused social media platform, when an
Icelandic bank froze their funds with no
real explanation. Well, now they're
fighting back, teaming up with Wikileaks
legal team in a case that could set a
global precedent and blow the lid off
how banks are being used to silence
disscent. Joining us is former CIA
whistleblower and pancquake spokesperson
John Kiryaku to explain what's really at
stake and why none of us are safe from
this if it goes unchecked. John, welcome
to the show. Thank you so much for being
here. Uh, thanks for the invitation,
Kim. Good to see you. This is one of
those things that people don't really
think about in the fight against
censorship and it is uh because it's it
it's happening more and more but it's
fairly rare. You know, most of us think
of censorship. We think being ripped off
social media. We think of being
demonetized even from certain platforms,
but debanking is a serious one. This is
where the bank institution says, "We're
no longer going to even do business with
you." Um, explain, first of all, tell us
what Pancquake is.
Sure. Pancake is a tech startup, but
it's a tech startup that does a lot of
different things, all of which are
focused on on both privacy and on
transparency. Uh it uh it uh for example
serves as a social media platform that
once it's it's actually out there up and
running, it's going to be competing with
the likes of Facebook and Twitter.
Secondly, it is a short URL service
where you can um you can take a URL, put
it into a pancake uh uh uh box and get a
shortened URL so that you cannot be
tracked on the internet while you're
surfing. Very valuable in terms of
privacy. And I'd like to comment if I
could, Kim, on on this whole issue of
debanking. Yeah, I think it's actually
more common than most Americans think.
When I was arrested after blowing the
whistle on the CIA's torture program, I
had not been convicted. I had just been
arrested. Bank of America sent me a
letter saying that they were closing my
accounts. I had been banking with Bank
of America for decades and they included
a check for the amount of money that I
had in my checking account and they said
that they no longer wanted to do
business with me. Wow. That was followed
Yeah. That was followed by USAA which
cancelled my homeowner's insurance and
my credit card as well as my car
insurance. Jeez. And then Yeah. And then
when I went out to find a new bank, for
example, there's a United Bank uh
walking distance from my my home. I went
in, I said, "Hi, I'd like to open a
checking account." They said, "Great.
Can I have your uh driver's license?" I
gave the driver's license. They put it
into the computer and the woman said,
"Oh, I'm sorry. We don't want to do
business with you. Wow. So, this is this
is actually more common than I think
most people realize. And and that's
before you weren't even convicted of
anything at this point. You had just
been arrested. That's it.
With Pancake, Susie Dawson, the chief
product officer, established the
company's finances in Iceland. Now,
they're in Iceland for a number of
reasons, all of which are really cool to
me. For example, the servers are even
powered by by like underwater hot
springs and steam power. It's really
amazing. It's a totally green company. I
absolutely love it for that reason. But
anyway, she opened the the company's
bank accounts in Iceland and then like
flipping a switch one day, the uh the
Bank of Iceland froze the accounts. Now
Susie's not only never been convicted of
any crime, she's never even been accused
of any crime. But what what is it about?
Right. But why what is it about Pancake
that made them want to do that?
Well, Pancquake I think there are a
couple of reasons. Pancake number one is
a threat to some very big, very powerful
and important companies. But number two,
it focuses on these issues of privacy,
security, and transparency at the same
time. And that I think is a threat to
powerful governments or governmental
organizations.
And
so a lot of Pancquake people, myself
included, have been supportive of
Wikileaks and Julian Assange and Ed
Snowden and this whole issue of of
transparency when it comes to national
security. And I think that very powerful
people, very powerful organizations have
deemed Pancquake to be some sort of
threat. And I think the idea was, and
I'm speculating here, right, but I think
the idea was uh to try to smother the
company in its crib. And that's just
simply not going to work. So Pancake has
not launched yet.
No, this has set us back. So there is an
there's an actual
documentable impact that the freezing of
these accounts has had and that's why
Pancake has decided to take legal
action. Yeah. Well, right. So, uh
because I've heard of Pancquake before.
I've been hearing about it for a year or
so, but I wasn't really sure what it was
and largely because it's not out yet. It
hasn't launched. So, um but this kind of
sounds a lot like what was that one
social media platform that they shut
down and it was it was a response to
Twitter, you know, when Twitter had gone
all sensory and then there was that
other one uh started with a P and it was
and then they they basically ripped it
off of all the app stores. They shut it
down completely and um do you remember
what the one I'm talking about? And this
was a I don't I remember mastadon and
blue sky and no this was one that they
that they had gone after I forgot the
name of it but they went after it and
they they completely got it shut down
basically before I mean it launched and
people were starting to migrate toward
it but they got it to be taken off all
the app stores and yeah I think they
even debanked them. I mean, it was just
like this terrible way to shut down uh
any sort of disscent. And it's this is
such a scary time to live in that that
they're able to use all of these various
tools to shut down disscent to strongarm
us into behaving, right? I mean,
everybody needs money to live. Unless
you've got your own garden in the back,
even then you're going to have to pay
property tax. So, you need money to live
at all. and and if they have the ability
to go in and just debank you completely
or halt your funds in some way uh take
you off the market. I mean, this this
type of stuff, this is so dystopian, so
scary. And and the thing about the
pancake, exactly right, the thing about
it that that makes this one even extra
scary is we don't even know why. From
everything I've read about Panquake,
there's no there was no explanation from
the bank, from the Icelandic bank. There
was no like this is why. It just
happened. It just happened. And listen,
I I will admit to you that that I have,
of course, I'm I'm a I'm a Pancake
employee, but I I will tell you, I know
these people. I like them. I trust them.
I wouldn't work with them if I didn't
trust them. These are good, honest,
hardworking, law-abiding people. This
move to freeze the accounts, this is a
political move. It's a political
strategy. But Pancake is handling it in
the right way. They've hired Wikileaks
Iceland attorneys. These are the Iceland
attorneys that have had success in the
Icelandic courts. I' I've attended uh
some of the uh the hearings. There's one
thing that I I didn't understand and and
well, I'll admit to you that I don't
like uh and that is in the Icelandic
legal system, there is no system of of
discovery. So we can't say that the bank
has to turn over all uh memos for
example or emails related to the
decision to to debank pancquake. What we
have to say is we think that there are
these memos out there and we want the
bank to turn over the memos. Well the
bank can just as easily say oh those
memos don't exist. There are no such
memos. Mhm. So, it's a little bit
tougher, but um we we've got the best
lawyers in the country and uh and we're
moving forward very quickly with this.
What happens, do you think, if you guys
win this case? I mean, will this prevent
has there been any other case yet? I'm
wondering that has tackled this. See,
see, this is not about the money. Yeah,
this is not about the money because the
the money has been has been unfrozen.
We've got the money and and we're we've
got two dozen employees. we're we're in
the process of getting our products out
there. This is not about the money. It's
about the principle and it's about the
precedent. And so I think you're right
and you were right during the intro that
this is going to send to send a
precedent not just to the government of
Iceland and to the uh to the banking uh
system uh in Iceland but to everybody
that you can't discriminate against
people. You can't target people just
because you don't like their politics.
Yeah. Or you don't like what you think
might be their politics. So I think this
is a very important case.
The US has some laws that when it comes
to banking that are so bizarre to me and
um like when they debanked you and they
were like well we don't like the fact
that you exposed US torture program
John. How dare you? How dare you? How do
you like that? Uh but the there's
there's this weird um idea and I I guess
I haven't really thought it through
fully. Maybe we can think it through.
But the the government takes a position
that a bank should not be um doing
business with like mobsters, right? So
they sure not a problem. Okay. But or is
it then? That's what I'm wanting to
think about like is it a problem? Only
only if there is documentable evidence
of some kind of crime like money
laundering let's say you you know the
whole concept of know your customer that
all these financial institutions have to
go through. But I don't think they
should. They don't want to be I don't
think they should know me. I don't think
they should know. I I don't think it's
any of their business what I do with my
money. Like if if I commit a crime, let
me deal with that and the government
will come after me and I'll go to jail
and that'll be that, right? But like why
does my banker need to know what I'm
spending my money on? I mean, I this how
or even how I'm making the money. This
decision should not be up to the bank,
right? It shouldn't be up to the bank. I
agree with you about that. So it's just
like the cell phone company. Should the
cell phone company be able to say, "You
know what? We're not going to issue you
a phone, uh, or we're shutting off your
phone service because we think you might
be committing crime with your phone."
Plenty of people commit crime with their
phones, and yet we're not that for
whatever reason, there's not that same
rule on like the cell phone companies
that there is on the banking system. The
banks are expected, for whatever reason,
I don't know where this comes from, but
the banks are expected to know their
customer and to get really involved in
the money. And I I I and and in some
cases, you know, I see a lot of people
that are the real even the the freedom
warriors, the non-censorship crowd, and
they'll get all in on this when it comes
to Yeah, but the Epstein stuff, right?
We want to know about the banks and the
Epstein and there was and Epstein was uh
getting this money and and um it was
nefarious and so the banks should have
known and and we're going to take down
Chase Bank, right? They've been going
after Chase for hey, you knew about
Epstein and all this stuff. And so a lot
of people want to cheer that on. But I
sit there and I think why I I I that
doesn't make unless the banker himself
like the bank the head of the bank was
at Epstein Island and actually engaging
in the in the nefarious activity, you
know, that but to I I don't think it
should
be, you know, a thing for banks to have
to know what the hell we're doing, how
we made our money, where the money came
from, where it's going. I don't think
they should know any of that. And I
don't I I'm trying to think of if
there's a good legitimate. So even in in
the most heinous of crimes like child,
you know, child trafficking, child
pornography, that type of stuff, right?
So that's like the most heinous crime
that we can all I think think of. And
we're all everybody's very against this.
And this is why Epstein triggers people
because then they say, "Yeah, we'll just
do whatever it takes to crack down on
the Epstein guy." Um, but even in that
most heinous crime of like child
trafficking, is it the bank's
responsibility to know that you received
this money because you were selling
little children for sex? I mean, that's
the worst thing I can think of. And I
still don't think it's the bank's
responsibility to or even their business
at all to know where my money came from,
where anybody's money came from. That's
up
to now if the bank suspects the bank may
want to tip off the police, right? It
might be in good moral and ethics for
the bank to say, uh, that's different.
But maybe, but even then, that's like a
privacy issue that, you know, like when
Apple held its ground and said, "We're
not cracking open the phone of this
terrorist." That's right. Right. Yes.
Um. Yes. So then it goes into that into
that question. Should you should you
then even if you do know that maybe this
person is a bad person like Apple
knowing yeah it's a terrorist but we're
still not going to unlock the phone. Um
you know is it is it the bank's
responsibility to tip off the
police? I you know these are the types
we these are the types of conversations
I guess we have to have in society
because this is this is where it's this
is where it started. It started and it
always starts with the good intentions,
right? That's where all of these
censorship laws start. And it started
off with we want to we want to prevent
the mobsters and the child traffickers.
So the bank should know their customer
and the bank should follow the money.
And if the money looks like it's coming
from someplace bad, then the bank should
be debunking this person. That's where
it comes from. That good intention. Shut
down the child trafficker.
Dick Cheney along the same lines. Dick
Cheney once said that he would rather he
would rather incarcerate a hundred
innocent men than to let one guilty one
go free. And I'm exactly the opposite.
And I think you are too. Right. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Just like I don't agree that
we should blow up a 100 people in order
to get one bad guy. I don't think that
the FBI should be allowed to storm into
a business building and massacre
everybody and then go on TV and say,
"Well, that's because we were going
after the one terrorist and they were
using the rest as human shields, so what
were we supposed to do?" You know, we
don't agree with that usually
fundamentally. Um, no, I'm with you.
But, but apparently Dick Cheney thinks
that that's okay. Well, a lot of people
clearly do think that's okay. Yeah,
apparently they do. But that's where it
starts. And I think that's what people
need to understand and reconcile because
I'm seeing this also with other
censorship stuff like right now I'm
seeing a lot of the anti-censorship
crowd very proensorship suddenly when it
comes to like Israel for example they're
suddenly like that's right yeah censor
them right uh and it's yeah that's
exactly right we have to be for the
principle even when we don't agree with
whatever you know like the child
trafficking is horrible and heinous but
I still don't think the bank should be
debanking
uh that you Oh, right. You you've heard
the old saying, I I disagree with what
you say, but I'll fight to the death for
your right to say it. Right. You know,
that's that should be all of our
positions here. You
know, Pancake is a very small company
compared to these other these titans of
technology. Yeah. Um it it's not a
threat to these titans, but the idea of
of transparency is the threat to them.
The idea of transparency is a threat to
some governments. I'm looking at you,
Washington, DC. And I think that's why
they're trying to snuff it out. Now,
we've been fortunate, too, in that we
have investors in Pancake who believe in
the company and who believe in its
principles and they've kept us going.
Now, of course, the bank has backed off
and has unfrozen the the funds, but um
but this is a bigger fight than just the
funds. This is a fight about principle,
and so we have to keep up this fight.
Yeah. No, you really do because it is um
we we've got to stop the debanking. I
just wonder though with this fight being
in Iceland, if it will affect any I
don't, you know, I doubt it'll affect
anyone in the United States. Uh maybe it
would affect people as well. Yeah. Is is
Iceland in the EU? Are they part of the
EU? It it has kind of a partnership with
the EU. When you go through immigration,
it's considered to be entering the EU,
but it doesn't use the Euro. Okay.
Yeah. I don't remember what Shenhen
status. Yeah, you're it says it is
Iceland is not a member of the EU, but
it is a member of the European Economic
Area and the Shenhen area. That's what
it is. So, it is in the Shenen zone.
Interesting. Uh, by the way, the app
that was taken off of all of the
services, the Twitter app was called
Parlor, and that's the one that in Oh, I
remember Parlor. Yeah. And they were
able to It was a conservative app,
right? And they were able to bury it
because they didn't like the voices that
were going to be on it. And it sounds
like that's similar to what's happening
to Panquake.
That's exactly right. What kind of a
dystopian world are we living in? Where
are we headed? Do you think, John, do
you think we're going to get better or
worse? Like, what's happening here?
I think things get worse before they get
better. Because even here in the United
States, you know, there's really no push
back from Democrats when Republicans are
in the White House and vice versa on
these big issues of censorship under the
guise of national security. They all
agree. They agree with one another. You
know, where where are the so-called
progressives? Where I'm not saying they
disappeared. Yeah. Yeah. When when you
look back through relatively recent
history, where are the Daniel Patrick
Moyahanss or the Frank Churches or Otis
Pikes? Where are these guys? They're all
dead and gone. The Ted Kennedy's,
they're all dead. And I I can't think of
anybody on Capitol Hill right now who I
would consider to be a giant, you know,
a philosopher like like Moahan was who
could lead us out of this wilderness.
There's nobody up there.
Well, and that's the problem. Those that
said they were going to fight for free
speech or whatever, you know, they're
just happy to censor just a topic that a
different topic. They want their topics
to be uncensored and they want to censor
other people's topics. And it is just
the hypocrisy going against the actual
just Oh my god. Yes. That's that's I'll
give you an example if I may. Last
night, last night I went to an event to
celebrate Arab ArabAmerican Heritage
Month. And uh it's a it's a big deal.
They do it every year. It's a beautiful
dinner and then they have a concert and
they have speakers. It's awesome. And so
this year it was supposed to be at the
Amazon headquarters in Arlington,
Virginia. They have a large facility and
there were about five or six hundred
people last night.
So 48 hours before the event, Amazon
canled it and said, "Oh no, you can't
come here." And they wouldn't give any
reason. Well, we know the
reason. So in just 48 hours, they had
to, it's the ArabAmerican Heritage
Foundation. They had to move the entire
event and they found a church hall at
the St. Peter and Paul um Antioch and
Orthodox Cathedral in PTOAC, Maryland.
Beautiful facility, but they were able
to move the whole thing there. Now, it's
nowhere near a subway. So, there were
like a hundred students from
universities that couldn't make it
because it's impossible to get there
unless you have a car. Um, and we had
speakers like Rashida Tale, for
example, prominent doctors from the
Arab-American community. And finally,
one of the speakers, Andy Shal, he's a
beloved uh restaurant tour here in
Washington. He owns a a local chain
called Bus Boys and Poets, which is
based on the concept of free speech. And
Andy said, "Look, let's call a spade a
spade." Amazon cancelled this because
they're trying to silence the
ArabAmerican community because the
message of the Arab-American community
is in support of human rights in Gaza,
anti- genocide in Gaza. And that doesn't
fit into Amazon's plan. And it's the
same thing with Pancake. It's the same
thing that is happening to Pancake and
to countless other companies and
organizations around the world. Yeah.
So much for free, you know, a free
country, free speech. So much for all of
that. Censorship is a real thing. Yeah.
And we have to constantly fight it.
Jeez. Um, thank you for talking to us
about Pancake and what's going on there.
I mean, I hope the fight I hope you guys
win the fight. I mean, I hope you guys
take it and and um and make some
progress on this cuz we do have to fight
these every single time. And like you
said, Pancake has the money back. It's
not about that. It's about the issue.
And we need more people fighting these
issues because it does I mean how else
are we going to have our freedom and and
we have to keep fighting for it. I mean
that's the whole got to keep fighting
for it. Um John tell everybody what
you're up to these days.
Oh thanks. I'm up to a bunch of things.
I have a show on a platform called
Unified Television. It's
unifyd. It's called CIA declassified.
And we take declassified CIA documents
and use them to tell stories through
history. Sometimes these stories are
kind of ugly things that the CIA did.
Um, I'm on u uh YouTube. I have two
podcasts. One with Ted Raw is called
Deep Program. The other is just myself,
Deep Focus with John Kuryaku. And I've
got my Substack. Oh, okay. John
Kuryaku.substack. Have you been diving
into those JFK files yet? Those
declassified? Yeah. You know, and and
they really do have some some real
nuggets that we've never known before.
What do you think is like the biggest um
like I guess bombshell from this latest
drop? The bombshell really is that James
uh Angleton, the former deputy director
of the CIA for counter intelligence, um
ordered CIA officers to recruit Lee
Harvey Oswald as a source. That's long
been speculated uh on and long dismissed
as a conspiracy theory. Was not a
conspiracy theory. It was the truth. And
for the very first time, people are
starting to look at the Israeli angle to
this whole thing. Yeah. Well, because
Angleton was clearly a MSAD double
agent. I mean, that guy was Oh my god. I
mean, how how just as an aside Yeah.
Angleton's best friend, and when I say
best friend, I mean they were best man
in each other's weddings. And Angleton
was the other guy's daughter's godfather
was his best friend was Kim Philby, one
of the most notorious traders in in
modern history. He was the he was the
director of the deputy director of MI6,
the British Intelligence Service. The
entire time he was a KGB double agent.
And when Angleton got burned, he just
assumed that everybody was a potential
double agent. He ruined lives, countless
lives by accusing everybody of being a
KGB mole. And meanwhile, he was a double
agent from Yeah. clearly. I mean, we
don't know for a fact, I guess, but I,
you know, but it's like highly
suspicious.
Yeah. Yeah. How what would be the mo I
mean, you were in the CIA. What's the
motivation for somebody to do that? And
how common do you think it was or is for
there to be CIA double agents? Like why
would these people betray the country
like this?
money. It's almost always about money.
Uh in counter intelligence training,
they they teach us that the motivation
for people accepting a pitch from us,
for example, 95% of the time is money.
The rest of the 5% uh is uh people are
um ideological. They just love the
United States, right? Or conversely,
love Israel, love communism, you know,
whatever. Um, and there's about 1% where
the motivation is revenge. They've been
passed over for promotion. They hate
their bosses. Somebody wronged them in
some way, and so they volunteer uh at
the CIA. But 95% of the time, it's
money. They'll just betray the country
for money.
Yeah. And in the 15 years that I was at
the CIA, we had um we had two moles and
uh and the FBI had a mole that you
found. we found. Yeah. And there's
always there's always been speculation
that there was a that there was a third
that we just didn't find.
Yeah. In fact, you know, Robert Hansen,
the FBI mole, was in charge of the FBI's
mole hunting team. And so, every time
they got close to figuring out that it
was him, he would
deflect. And he accused U. Brian Kelly,
a friend of mine at the CIA of being a
mole. Brian was fired and threatened
with the death
penalty. And then finally, when they
revealed it was Hansen. And the only
reason they were able to figure it out
it was Hansen is because they got a
short recording of the mole um speaking
with his KGB handler. Uh everybody was
gathered around the table to listen to
the recording thinking we finally got
Brian Kelly. and they played the
recording and it was Hansen, their
boss. Uh he went to the dead drop site
which was under a little pedestrian
bridge in a park in Vienna, Virginia and
they got him. He died a year ago in
Supermax in Florence, Colorado. Wow.
Yeah.
Have was there ever a mole that was uh
or any sort of double agent that was
found for Israel? Has that ever been
cracked down or was it always like other
countries? Jonathan Pard. Jonathan Pard.
Uh we got him we got him fair and
square. He was sentenced to 30 years. He
did every single day of the 30 years.
And uh when he was expelled, he was on
the first flight to Israel on an Israeli
government plane. They gave him Israeli
citizenship and a parade when he got
home. Oh gosh.
Why? How is this country our greatest
ally? I I just don't understand it like
this. Well, I'll leave you I'll leave
you with one other thought. Yeah, on my
very first day at the CIA, you know, you
put your hand in the air, you swear to
uphold and protect the Constitution
against all enemies, domestic and
foreign, and uh we had a speech by the
CIA's director of security. And he was
talking about counter intelligence. And
he said that at the Israeli embassy here
in Washington, there are two declared uh
intelligence officers, one for Mossad,
which is external intu intelligence, and
one for Shinbet, which is the Israeli
version of the FBI. And he said, "The
FBI has been able to
identify 187 undeclared Israeli
intelligence agents all across the
United States, mostly trying to
infiltrate our defense contractors to
steal our defense secrets. Even though
we give the Israelis 99% of our defense
secrets, they want that last 1% for
themselves."
And they spy on us to get it
constantly.
greatest ally everybody. Greatest ally.
Say that. John, thank you so much for
being here uh and giving us the insight
into Pancake and and everything else.
Best of luck to you. We have the links
down below to all of the projects that
you're working on. Um appreciate your
time, John. It's always a pleasure.
Thanks for for doing this.
Thank you for watching this clip from
the full Kim Iverson show, which you
could catch Monday through Friday, 2:00
p. p.m. Pacific, 5:00 p. p.m. Eastern,
by going to kim Iverson showow.com.
You'll catch it live. It is free to
watch. 2:00 p.m. Pacific, 5:00 p.m.
Eastern. See you there.